<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>DamageControl</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <date>11/09/2004</date>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Aslak</firstname>

        <surname>Hellesøy</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>ThoughtWorks Inc.</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Jon</firstname>

        <surname>Tirsen</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>ThoughtWorks Inc.</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Lars</firstname>

        <surname>Trieloff</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>What is DamageControl</title>

    <para>DamageControl is a continous integration system that helps you to
    keep feedback about build failures. If you are working on a project that
    is supervised by DamageControl and one of your team members commits
    changes to the Software Configuration Management System, DamageControl
    will detect the changes to the codebase and attempt to build a integration
    build of your project.</para>

    <para>If this integration build succeeds, everything is OK. The green
    light shows up and you can continue your work. If the recent changes have
    broken the build, your project is damaged. DamageControl helps you to
    <quote>control the damage before the damage controls you</quote>. The
    first step is that the team members who have broken the build are
    informed. There are different ways to do it, they can receive an EMail, an
    instant message, an issue could be filed in the issue tracker or a status
    monitor at their desktop could show a red light.</para>

    <para>In the next step, the objected changes could be rolled back, so that
    the project is in an consistant state again. The damager will repair the
    damage and everyone else will continue to work.</para>

    <para>What distinguishes DamageControl from other continuous integration
    systems like CruiseControl or CruiseControl.NET?</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl is under heavy development. If you want to use
        something rock solid and do not care for the newest features, stop
        reading here.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl is platform agnostic. You can build your project
        with Java, Ant, Ruby, .NET, Nant, Make or whatever tools you
        like.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl is easy to use and offers simple, web-based
        configuration. No need to edit XML files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl is self-contained. It comes with an own runtime
        and an embedded webserver.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl has many channels to notify users of successful or
        failed builds. And it is very easy to create your own notification
        channel.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl supports as many projects as you need and your
        build server can handle. It is even possible to run multiple builds at
        once.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl builds are triggered by CVS or Subversion on every
        commit. It can install the triggers for you and supports polling, if
        it is impossible to use triggers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DamageControl integrates with tools like ViewCVS or Fisheye as
        well as Jira, Bugzilla and Scarab.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In this documentation you will find everything needed for running
    and configuring DamageControl. Additionally you will find information
    important if you would like to implement extensions to DamageControl to
    make it fit your specific needs.</para>

    <para>Before you decide that you do not need a program like DamageControl,
    because it does not help you to create more shiny new code in shorter
    time, consider the advantages of detecting problems early: The sooner a
    problem is detected, the cheaper it is to fix it.</para>

    <para>If you identify problems during requirements engineering, you can
    talk with the customer and the problem is gone. If you identify problems
    during the design phase, you have all opportunities to find a design that
    will avoid those problems. If you occur problems during the
    implementation, you can still fix bugs and create workarounds for other
    issues. Trying to correct a problem in an already deployed system is very
    hard and expensive.</para>

    <para>So DamageControl helps you to identify problems early, to solve
    identified problems and to produce high-quality-software cost-efficient
    while keeping your schedules.</para>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>User Manual</title>

    <section>
      <title>Installing DamageControl</title>

      <section os="unix">
        <title>Linux, UNIX, Mac OS X</title>

        <para>To install DamageControl on a server with an UNIX-like operating
        system, follow these steps.</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Download Ruby, version 1.8.2_pre2 or later from the <ulink
            url="http://www.ruby-lang.org/">Ruby Homepage</ulink>. In most
            cases it is not required to install Ruby manually, as most Linux
            distributions have prepared packages of Ruby available, which can
            be installed using the distribution's packet manager.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Install a client for the SCM system you are using on the
            build server. Supported version control systems are
            currently:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><ulink
                url="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</ulink></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>the <ulink url="http://www.cvshome.org/">Concurrent
                Versioning System</ulink> (CVS)</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Download DamageControl from the <ulink
            url="http://dist.codehaus.org/damagecontrol/distributions/">DamagControl
            download page</ulink>. There is one distribution tarball for every
            successful build and in most cases the latets build is the best
            choice.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Unpack the tarball to a directory of your choice. Define a
            environment variable <envar>DAMAGECONTROL_HOME</envar> which
            points to the directory where you unpacked the archive.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>Additionally it could be useful to install an Apache Web Server
        to allow configuration of access privileges, a Mail server to send
        notification messages per EMail, or an IRC server.</para>

        <para>If you are using mail notifications, the optimal way to inform
        your developers is using a mailing list. Everyone who is subscribed to
        the mailing list will receive the notification, but DamageControl can
        still send mails to individual developers.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Gentoo Linux</title>

          <para>Users of Gentoo Linux can take advantage of a ebuild that wil
          automatically install DamageControl. Follow these instructions to
          install the ebuild.</para>

          <procedure>
            <step>
              <para>Open the file <filename>/etc/make.conf</filename> and
              define the variable <varname>PORTDIR_OVERLAY</varname>. This
              variable contains a list of directories portage uses to search
              for ebuild.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Change to one of the directories defined before.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Download the ebuilds.</para>

              <screen><prompt># </prompt><userinput>wget http://www.goshaky.com/goshaky-distfiles/gentoo/damagecontrol-ebuild.tar.bz2</userinput></screen>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Unpack the tarball.</para>

              <screen><prompt># </prompt><userinput>tar -jxvf damagecontrol-ebuild.tar.bz2</userinput></screen>
            </step>
          </procedure>

          <para>DamageControl can be installed by typing <literal>emerge
          damagecontrol</literal> on the command line. If you would like to
          use HTTP authentification, you should have the use-flag
          <literal>apache2</literal> set.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section os="windows">
        <title>Windows</title>

        <para>Users of the Microsoft WIndows Operating System can install
        DamageControl using the installer. You do not need to download a
        separate Ruby runtime, as it is included in the installer.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the DamageControl Server</title>

      <para>Users of DamageControl under Microsoft Windows can start
      DamageControl using the created entries in the Start menu. On other
      platforms, starting
      <filename><envar>DAMAGECONTROL_HOME</envar>/bin/damagecontrol</filename>
      is the preferred solution. This script expects a configuration file as
      command line argument.</para>

      <caution>
        <para>It is very dangerous to run DamageControl as
        <literal>root</literal>-user. It is better to create a new user, which
        has read and write access to <envar>DAMAGECONTROL_HOME</envar> and
        <envar>DAMAGECONTROL_WORK</envar>, but cannot access other user's
        files.</para>
      </caution>

      <para>A default configuration is provided in the file
      <filename><envar>DAMAGECONTROL_HOME</envar>/bin/server.rb</filename>. If
      you would like to make changes to the configuration, you should create a
      copy of <filename>server.rb</filename> and edit and use this
      configuration file.</para>

      <para>The following sections cover example configurations for a number
      of purposes. All these configurations are optional and not needed if you
      just want to test DamageControl.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Access Control</title>

        <para>By default everyone can access the DamageControl server and add
        projects or change configurations. This is not useful if you want to
        have an public build server, because you do not want to allow
        strangers to change the configuration of your DamageControl
        server.</para>

        <para>This configuration involves two steps. Firstly you have to
        configure DamageControl to allow connections only from the local
        machine. Secondly you have to create a Apache proxy server that will
        serve the DamageControl pages.</para>

        <para>To modify the DamageControl configuration follow these
        steps.</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Open your DamageControl server configuration file in a text
            editor.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the section which configures the network server. This
            section looks in the default configuration like this:</para>

            <programlisting>server = DamageControlServer.new(
  :RootDir =&gt; ENV["DAMAGECONTROL_WORK"],
  :HttpPort =&gt; 4712,
  :PollingInterval =&gt; 60 # specified in seconds
  # to allow access only from localhost then uncomment line below 
  # (when running behind an Apache proxy for example)
  #:AllowIPs =&gt; [ "127.0.0.1" ],
  )</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Change the lines to this configuration to allow access only
            from the local machine. If your webserver is running on a
            different machine, you should replace <literal>127.0.0.1</literal>
            with the IP-address of the remote webserver.</para>

            <programlisting>server = DamageControlServer.new(
  :RootDir =&gt; ENV["DAMAGECONTROL_WORK"],
  :HttpPort =&gt; 4712,
  :PollingInterval =&gt; 60,
  :AllowIPs =&gt; [ "127.0.0.1" ]
  )</programlisting>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>In order to serve the DamageControl pages from an ordinary web
        server, install a web server and configure it to work as a proxy for
        DamageControl. An example configuration for the Apache webserver is
        like this.</para>

        <programlisting>ProxyRequests off
RewriteEngine On
ProxyPass /public http://localhost:4712/public
ProxyPassReverse /public http://localhost:4712/public
ProxyPass /private http://localhost:4712/private
ProxyPassReverse /private http://localhost:4712/private</programlisting>

        <para>This configuration passes all requests to
        http://servername/public and http://servername/private to the
        corresponding locations of the DamageControl server. To add
        authentification to the private configuration parts, you should append
        following lines to the Apache configuration.</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;Location /private&gt;
        AuthName "DamageControl"
        AuthType Basic
        AuthUserFile /etc/apache2/dc.passwd
        Require valid-user
&lt;/Location&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>No user will be able to access the web configuration interface
        of the DamageControl server, unless the user has provided a
        username-password-configuration that is included in the password file
        <filename>/etc/apache2/dc.passwd</filename>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Multiple Build Executors</title>

        <para>DamageControl has the ability to run multiple build parallel.
        Each build will be executed by one build executor. The default
        configuration includes only one build executor, so if this executor is
        in use and a new build is triggered, the build will queued in the
        build queue.</para>

        <para>If you would like to build two projects at once, you have to
        define a new build executor. To do this, follow these steps.</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Open your DamageControl server configuration file in a text
            editor.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the line</para>

            <programlisting>def server.init_build_executors</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Insert following code behind this line.</para>

            <programlisting>build_scheduler.add_executor(
  BuildExecutor.new(
    'executor2', 
    hub, 
    project_directories, 
    build_history_repository))</programlisting>

            <para><literal>executor2</literal> is the name of the new
            executor. This name must be unique for one DamageControl server
            installation.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>For each additional build executor, repeat the last step but
            do not forget to select a unique name for each executor.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring DamageControl Projects</title>

      <para>If you have installed DamageControl and set up DamageControl to
      fit your needs, it is time to configure projects DamageControl will
      build. This is very easy as you can use the web interface for almost all
      tasks.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating Projects</title>

        <para>In order to create a new project, open the private dashboard of
        the DamageControl server. If DamageControl is running on your local
        machine, the URL is usually <ulink
        url="http://localhost:4712/private/dashboard">http://localhost:4712/private/dashboard</ulink>,
        if DamageControl is running behind an Apache proxy, open <ulink
        url="http://hostname/private/dashboard">http://hostname/private/dashboard</ulink>.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>An empty private dashboard</title>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/new_project.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>A new project is created by following the <guilabel>New
        project</guilabel> hyperlink.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DamageControl and Build Tools</title>

        <para>Following environment variables are passed to an external build
        process. You can use these variables to create build artifacts which
        are specific to a certain build.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><envar>DAMAGECONTROL_CHANGES</envar></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Contains the relative path of each modified file since
              last successful build, separated by whitespaces</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><envar>DAMAGECONTROL_BUILD_LABEL</envar></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Contains the build number as determined by
              damagecontrol</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DamageControl and SCM Systems</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DamageControl and Issue Trackers</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>DamageControl Notifications</title>

      <section>
        <title>Send EMails on build</title>

        <para>By default DamageControl will send no notification messages on
        each build. In oder to send EMails on successful or failed build, you
        have to configure an EMail publisher. To do this, follow these
        steps.</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Open your DamageControl server configuration file in a text
            editor.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find following line.</para>

            <programlisting>def server.init_custom_components</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Add following code below this line.</para>

            <programlisting>require 'damagecontrol/publisher/EmailPublisher'
component(:email_publisher, EmailPublisher.new(hub, build_history_repository,
  :SubjectTemplate =&gt; "short_text_build_result.erb", 
  :BodyTemplate =&gt; "short_html_build_result.erb",
  :FromEmail =&gt; "damagecontrol@mydomain.com",
  :MailServerHost =&gt; "localhost",
  :MailServerPort =&gt; 25))</programlisting>

            <para>Replace <literal>damagecontrol@mydomain.com</literal> with
            the desired sender address and <literal>localhost</literal> with
            the hostname of the mail server.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Publish to IRC server</title>

        <para>Publishing build results to an IRC server requires similar
        configuration of an IRC publisher. This is done by following these
        steps.</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Open your DamageControl server configuration file in a text
            editor.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find following line.</para>

            <programlisting>def server.init_custom_components</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Add following code below this line.</para>

            <programlisting>require 'damagecontrol/publisher/IRCPublisher'
component(:irc_publisher, 
  IRCPublisher.new(
    hub, 
   "some.irc.server", 
   '#somechannel', 
   "short_text_build_result_with_link.erb"))</programlisting>

            <para>Replace <literal>some.irc.server</literal> with the hostname
            of your IRC server and <literal>somechannel</literal> with the
            channel name.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>RSS</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Windows System Tray</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>GNOME System Tray</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Developer Handbook</title>

    <para></para>
  </chapter>
</book>